I think what I might do is uh we don't
finish the meditation
section today I'll pick it up on
TR
okay and then between we'll go on to
emptiness for the for the residents
okay okay here we
go I
think which is yeah okay
we're in the middle of the
five and we've been
discussing uh detecting when your mind
is uh too low or too high
right I don't know I don't know if
everyone was here this morning at 9:30
for the meditation at the yoga studio
but uh basically we tried to do 8
minutes on the object and it was hard
and it was exhausting uh
so but what happens if you do if you do
real meditation it's like doing a real
yoga pose with a tough teacher who
demands proper alignment right at the
beginning uh it's harder and it feels
uncomfortable and then later
everything's easier because you're doing
it right
so so maybe try short sessions you know
do your preliminaries and then do do
don't go for an hour you see what I mean
go for 10 good minutes uh then if you
want to do a Thanksgiving meditation for
50 minutes that's okay but really
concentrated single pointed meditation 8
minutes is pretty
good all
right and people who say they're doing
more are are probably not they don't
have watch pets and they're not even
aware that they're off the altar you see
what mean
the function of watchfulness the little
spy of Lookout that you put in your mind
is can be compared to holding inet uh
you didn't have handles on things like
you you drank tea out of a bowl small
bowl called a Cora a small wooden Bowl
so he said if you have tea in your pora
and you're holding it with your hand and
then there's a distinction between
holding it and holding it firmly and
then a state of awareness of whether or
not it's tipping right and you have it
already you didn't have it when you were
b as AG you know when you were Oney old
your mother put something in your hand
and you you you could hold it but you
didn't hold it tightly and it fell along
and then uh
later uh you learned to hold it more
tightly but you didn't hold it straight
and you you you were spilling stuff on
yourself for a while and now you just
hold a cup of of tea and you don't think
about it you don't think oh I have to
hold it I have to hold it tight enough
and I have to make sure the tea doesn't
swap out on either side you don't think
about it anymore good meditation is like
that you will get to a point where
you're not thinking about am I hitting
this garbage cans or this garbage cans
am I am I is my mind getting too dull or
is my mind wandering off you see you
won't have to think about about that it
will be like holding a cup of tea when
you first learn to drive your your your
driving teacher has to tell you no no
correct that to the right correct back
to the left and then now it's just
reflexive right you're just you're just
going like this you're talking on your
cell phone you're listening to music
you're half watching the road but this
part is just automatic right later your
meditation will be like that
same
way your awareness right I'm not talking
your Lookout that's a different word
right jba means your
awareness the the the part of your mind
which is holding on to the object your
awareness it's dble check it is holding
the object in a way which is
[Music]
firm and then the lookout is checking do
we it checks in every once in a while
with the mind says do we have any
dullness here do we have any uh
restlessness here okay if that part of
your mind Shing watchful watchfulness
it's like checking in once in a while
and seeing do I have do I have awareness
or Not In Yoga it's like I don't know
you would have a part of your mind
saying is my breath smooth or not you
know you go through an awesome series
and then part of your mind should be
checking in from time to time you know
in my breathing deep and smoothly or am
I holding a through
the you must
maintain this these two we call
say's job awareness's job is just to
hold the object's mind watchfulness job
is to watch whether awareness has lost
the object or not right it
I and they're different and you need
both of them if detects a problem if
watchfulness detects a problem it raises
an alarm it rings a bell and then Gemma
comes back and grabs the object you see
it grabs the object
again and then he
says in there's a science which one day
we should study together okay there's a
very very sophisticated presentation of
psychology in Buddhist scripture there
are 5251 mental functions are defined
and uh shishan watchfulness is not one
of them and and
so is saying well where in the where in
the classical functions of the Mind
shall we put watchfulness and he says
throw it in with wisdom okay throw it in
with wisdom it is a kind of
discrimination
it's it's an ability to discriminate do
we have a problem here or don't we have
a problem here so it's a kind of wisdom
it's a form of
wisdom uh the fourth classical
meditation problem
is you sure the a down
as these guys are I think it was Jenny's
class
you got
any it's down as far as you can go
freeze these
[Music]
mother
um if you do detect that your mind has
gotten too too low or too high right
then you have to take action you have to
do something okay the correction
uh problem number four is not you didn't
do anything like he rang the bell and
and you didn't do anything Shin R rang
the bell the watch gu look out rang the
bell then you don't do anything so when
when you become aware that you're off
the object or you're or that you're
getting dull or that you're thinking
about Lun then you have to do something
not to do something is problem number
four guess what the antidote to problem
number four is all right
once the lookout has detected that you
have dness or
restlessness he doesn't let it go on
anymore
jumu right after it pops up right after
you fall into dullness or right after
you start almost thinking about dinner
CH whether
uh
dull uh subtle dullness or whether it's
gross or subtle dullness or restlessness
so you have to apply the appropriate
antidote and we haven't gone through the
antidotes yet and and that's what we're
going to do now there's different
antidotes for rough dness there's a
different one for subtle dness there's a
different one for rough restlessness and
there's a different one for sub
so you got to decide to do
something this is similar to a case
where uh you know a military Lookout
runs back to base camp and says you know
there's somebody there we need help then
everyone what do you call it
[Music]
oh well what kind of reinforcements do
you need because every enemy is
different right if the Tank's coming you
need anti-tank gun if the Jet's coming
you need the what you
call okay AR whatever okay
okay here these are very important for
you this is part you should
remember which implies that you can
forget the rest
right if you detect subtle dullness okay
what would it feel
like you do
have you do have
fixation you do
have but there's no run there's no
there's no
okay I got
you there's no
uh what do you call it intensity
intensity there's no intensity okay so
if you detect that your mind is not in
the favorite piece of music did you
catch my favorite piece of music what
was it
today
huh the last song I mean come on I mean
I it makes me cry when I hear that song
you
did you know I mean when I hear that my
mind is and the mind goes into the music
and just St thing right if you detect
that you're not doing that you have to
take action got it it's very interesting
it's very interesting we are not
satisfied with half ass meditation we
are not satisfied with fairly good you
know fixation we're not satisfied with
that if you detect that you are not
happy having a favorite song in the
world experience You' got to do
something all right and if you don't
you've made this mistake and that's
tough I me it's tough to maintain a
favorite piece of music State of Mind
for more than the piece of music it's 9
minutes and 14
seconds it's difficult to to maintain
with your partner you know I mean it's
it's difficult to maintain you know like
this loveby duby thing for more than a
few minutes right now he's demanding
that if you don't feel lovey doy you
have to do something right away right
he's demanding a certain quality of the
meditation and less is not good enough
less is not good if you're not totally
lost in the meditation as you would be
lost in your
favorite in the
last then you're not it's not good
enough you have to take action see
because you would be tempted not to take
action right oh it's going fairly well
gra Michael not good
we want Mar we want what's that
intensity we want we want you lost in
the meditation okay all right so what
happens if you're not what do you do
right this is not oh yeah okay this is
not maybe the the box is
not uh
um he says son dness is Sam shimba Sam
shimba means the mind got a little bit
low shumba means like how you
feel um if you heard some slightly bad
news you you feel a little bit low like
you got a little bit of bad news so you
feel low s
whether you call it getting love or what
you call it
vness Z is basically the same
thing even though you have fixation and
even though you do have some freshness
of the
Mind
the the the altitude of
the the altitude of the holding of the
object has
dropped you're lower you're lower than
you should
be there's no there's no
intensity if you detect
it means you don't have to break your
meditation session you don't have to get
up don't break your meditation stay on
the cushion stay with your eyes
closed and don't switch objects okay so
subtle subtle dullness is taken care of
in inside the meditation you don't
switch to another object and you don't
stop Med you don't open your eyes you
stay in and you do the fixing
inside
send all you have to do is tighten up a
bit tighten up slightly on the other
tight tighten down slightly on the
other in the way that you would tighten
your hand slightly if the cup were about
to fall you see just tighten SL what it
means to tighten slightly and how it
feels the tighten slightly you won't
know until until January or whatever
right it's it's it's I can't explain it
in in words okay what does it mean to
tighten your mind butly you'll
see going from not so favorite music to
being deep inside your favorite piece of
music that's tightening see the
difference that's called
tightening it doesn't mean you you
know people do
[Music]
kapal but if you tighten down too
much you will get Restless the mind will
get Restless all
right it's a constant process of
Correction if you are not constantly
correcting your meditation you are in
settle D got
it if you're not doing this you know if
you're not saying oh I'm going this way
let me go back this way let me go back
this way if you're just sitting there
and not thinking like that something's
wrong for
most
WR
away get away
uh if you feel that you're about to
think about lunch then loosen up a
little so what has just happened you
detected that you weren't so deep as you
wanted to
be then you tightened up a bit then you
went too far in the tightening and then
you have to loosen a
bit good
Lord Buddha himself when he was
discussing meditation compared it to the
string on a
guitar it's a loot okay a he he compared
it to a string on a musical instrument
he said uh if it's too tight you go the
no go sour if it's to lose the no Sal
you have to find raino say raino it's
not okay it's Rambo Rambo
means uh appropriate amount rbo means
the appropriate amount not too tight not
too loose uh meditation by the time you
hit problem
number four is all about uh appropriate
amount raino know don't tighten too much
and don't loosen too much but
necessarily you're going to be going
like this right you you will tighten a
little too much and then you have to
come
back if you feel like your mind's about
to think about lunch lighten up a
bit but then if you feel like you're
getting a little bit drowsy or dull uh
do
then tighten up a bit all right that's
maybe the opposite of what you might
expect if you're getting dull tighten if
you're getting distracted loosen I think
to say you should loosen when you're
feeling distracted is is maybe
counterintuitive so so remember that one
if you're starting to think about much
loosen up on the object of it that that
seems opposite of what you should do
right what's the point at which you're
getting D or what's the point at which
you're getting restless or what's the
point at which tightening down is
causing a
problem you will only know from from
practice he says you can only know it
from practice
if your Lookout is not a clever one is
not a sharp guy jungle means sharp
guy remember used to love that one you
know you would drop a plate and he'd say
oh you're so
junle you're a really smart
guy it's difficult to know when you're
sliding off the scale you went too far
on the tiing or you went too far
listeni there's a very very famous early
Buddhist Master called in in India
called tandi Chand and he wrote a verse
about how it feels to try to track
whether you've gone too far or not far
enough in loosening up or tightening up
here's what he
said every time I try to do something
like like
every time I exert myself inside of
meditation to get some kind of result I
start to get distracted I start to get
Restless if I give up my my effort and
loosen up a bit then my mind drops and I
get
D I have trouble finding the line the
steady line between you know the Mind
wandering and the mind being D I have
trouble staying there in the the middle
like a driving a
car what the hell am I going to do with
this mind my all right I mean
l says it would appear that this High
Master of the past is expressing
some pretended
[Music]
difficulty in means you can't say a Lama
can't say of an ancient Master oh you
know he was having trouble in his
meditation he has to say he was
pretending to have trouble in his
meditation for our benefit he was
expressing the frustration of
controlling his mind and keeping it
going to on a middle path but it was
just pretending all
right that's just
uh Buddhist etiquette about high llamas
and high
Masters it would seem that they have
misspelled every Mantra since about
[Music]
okay this is a this is a very famous
line and it's very important
okay uh what do you call up uh Benedict
Arnold yeah yeah okay uh the the the
pery of it
perity anyway the bad thing about it
being that he was on our side right he
was one of our our own in in in the army
or you know Marines they would say he
was one of our own and then he turned
right or the CIA they'd say he was one
of our own and any turn uh your own
mind uh going especially into subtle
dness is is a
benedicto right and it's hard to catch a
turn coat in your own ranks that's the
that's the that's what he says that's
what the Tibetan means here uh somebody
who's coming from from another country
with a gun to shoot you is one thing but
somebody on your own side working in the
Central Command of the CIA who turns now
that's a problem because they're so hard
to recognize there it's so hard to know
who turned and in your own mind when it
goes to subtle dth is is what do you
call it
impersonating uh or it's pretending to
be your friend and and you think he's on
your side and you feel great in your
meditation right you don't have those
eight minutes of torture that we had
this morning of really holding on to the
object settle dness feels great you can
keep it up for an hour and a half you
can tell all your friends I meditate for
an hour and a half you know and then
this guy who seems to be on your side is
really your enemy within your own mind
and more difficult to detect a turn coat
in your own central office
[Music]
it's very difficult to detect subtle
dness within the central command of your
own skull right and you're going to have
to get good you're going to have to
develop a skill at detecting when
someone in your own mind has turned
right
[Music]
if you
try to tighten down a bit when you are
having subtle B all right if you try to
tighten down a bit when you are having
subtle but if you still feel like you
don't have
that strings intensity of your favorite
song all right if you still feel like
I'm not getting it
you know yes said I shouldn't be
satisfied till I I have the feeling that
I have with my favorite song and I'm not
there and I tried to tighten down a bit
and it didn't it didn't work I I still
don't feel the favorite song thing yet
in fact I'm I feel kind of irrita all
right this is kind of a mown of the
mind or you feel like or you feel like
it's just not happening
in fact sometimes the effort to tighten
down will throw you into obvious th you
get tired we were talking about it today
after the 8 minutes you just got tired
and you and you got obvious DS you got
tired you lost all energy you lost your
energy Master famous
uh presentation of the lower Middle Way
School Master B Rea said when your mind
feels a
little like you're feeling a little bit
down the Mind feels down no energy right
if you get there he said open up your
meditation open it in that case just
open it wider open up the whole thing
wider means open it wide what's that
mean you have there's a expression in
tibetan that doesn't have a good
English like about 10,000 others but
um when you go to sleep it's liar in the
yoga tradition it's like liar when you
go to
sleep the mind uh what you call it
retracts from the world right what do
you call
it it withdraws yeah good when you go to
sleep the Mind withdraws from the world
right and it comes in in in in and then
you fall as asleep if you can't withdraw
the Mind from the world when you lay
your head down on the pillow you get
insomnia right so the process of
sleeping is is drawing the mind in the
process of tightening down on an
is similar it is a drawing in of the of
the mind it is
a withdrawal of the mind to a smaller
Point like
that and he says
uh if you still have some dness and you
can't get to the favorite song
surrendered into the music thing if you
can't get to that state the problem is
you've withdrawn too much you have come
down to too small so he said open it up
B okay so physically you can even
imagine in your mind that that you have
tightened down to too small of a ball
and then release it a little bit and and
let it give it a little space create a
little space in your mind like
[Music]
that release
the open up J means open up the object a
little bit open it up a little bit make
it bigger
if that doesn't work all
right and and you're going to have to
learn these things
why when it comes time in wherever you
are or in Prescott you can't just have
the book there oh what do you do can get
let me see uh I don't remember what I
supposed to do oh TI up oh if I Tien up
too much yeah oh if the yeah okay let me
go back you know it's not going to work
like that the reason to have this class
uh now and then do the retreat what two
months from now or something is that you
go home and and learn it so that you
know it with your eyes closed because in
January you can't have a book in Fr you
all right so so especially these parts
especially this page about the antidotes
uh and tomorrow you'll have the
translation I think uh you can purchase
the transl you can purchase it online
it's called called Liberation in our
hands I think volume three you can buy
it on Amazon uh or you can we'll have
some here tomorrow the Publishers sent
us a big box p and they said whatever
you sell you sell whatever you don't you
send back so you know we're not doing it
for money we're just doing you can have
the book that I'm describing you can
have it with you and then you can you
can review this stuff so that in January
when you're there with your eyes closed
you know what to do right
still it does
work I really like this word um it it's
stuck with me for 20 30 years and I love
the word I don't know why um if you
still have a problem if you still can't
get into the object as deeply as your
favorite song Drop the object move to a
different object you're allowed to drop
the object for a for a few minutes let
go of the
object and then s say
s I learned the word
because when I got the how we used to
sit at the breakfast table and I was
with my his other student his other main
Student Art angle and he and art would
talk in
tobet and then I had already learned to
speak some tobet
and then uh I would say something in
tibetan he'd say you're not allowed to
speak Tibetan you have to speak English
and I said why and he said because I
have to learn English you know and of
course I got jealous of art so so he got
to speak tobet at the meals and I wasn't
allowed to speak tobet at
all I rarely see this kind of thing
going on with my students
because karma doesn't work um but anyway
uh I was extremely jealous for years and
uh so I did this thing I subscribed to a
Tibetan
newspaper and I would just lay it down
on The Breakfast Table and I would
ignore them and I would read the
newspaper and uh I got to this word s
and I was like what's s and he said s is
a metal that they give you for something
special like you're a military person or
you get a medal it's called a s s means
like recognition or that means a sign
right l s means uh of uh what do you
call achievement or promotion like that
so here s means promote the mind uh
uplift the Mind do do an
uplifter do some kind of uplifter
okay
s work on uplifting the mind or
go
uh think of something that will make you
happy or think of something that would
lift your spirits okay s means lift your
spirits gawa means that would make you
happy he gives
examples
means there are 6 billion people in the
world right now there are 6 billion
people in the world don't
know every single action they undertake
in their entire day and their entire
life is meaningless and is mistaken it
cannot lead to what they want even
making a cup of
tea even the way 6 billion people think
they are making a cup of tea is wrong
and they are not enjoying tea because
they got a tea bag or they got water or
they got honey all right that isn't why
they got a tea and none of them
understands thatu they want tea they
work they go to the store and they buy
tea bags they go to the faucet and they
turn on the water then they go to the
stove for which they're paying an
electrical bill and they heat up the
water and they pour it into the tea bag
and then they add some sweetener and
they think they are making a cup of tea
even with that six billion people are
grossly mistaken and they suffer because
of that six billion people suffer all
day long and all lifelong because they
don't even know how to make a cup of tea
how do you make a cup of tea you serve
it to someone else it's the only way you
can get a cup of te tea it has nothing
to do with working buying the
tea heating the water those are useless
unrelated actions they are not related
to getting a cup of tea you want tea
serve the hungry serve those who need
things right it's
it's it's a massive Global era repeated
by six billion people constantly all day
long and because of that they suffer
they they they compete they fight for
resources they fight for a job they
fight for
oil when the opposite is what would
bring them food and and it's a massive
Planet full
of violent suffering because they just
don't get it all right you are sitting
in this room you know out of 6 billion
people there are 200 people or something
sitting in this
and they are getting a tiny inkling of
how to make a cup of tea you see just a
tiny thing they're just thinking maybe
he's right maybe that's how I get te you
know out of six billion people you made
it to this room out of six billion
people you have a chance you have a tiny
chance you made it to this room are you
special or
not are you special or not are you like
the most extraordinary person in the
world or what you know you are one out
of 300 million so I don't the M but
anyway okay you are one out of really
you are one out of 300 million who's on
the verge of understanding where tea
comes from or how life itself
occurs and and I'd say you're pretty
special all right you are special that's
s if you get to a state in your medit
where it's get it's too D and you can't
get the mind up you have trouble getting
the mind up and and interested and
excited and feeling inspired then think
about the 6 billion people thing and if
you don't get inspired by that then you
know okay you you are extremely rare you
are one out of 300 million people really
I'm not I'm not exaggerating you are one
out of 300 million people who made it
here by extraordinary Good Karma you
know by extraordinary Deeds of kindness
in your paast you made it into this
world you're special you are
extraordinary you know you can save
planets with with what you're learning
you are special and you
will think about the if if that doesn't
make you happy think about how cool your
teacher is or the Buddha is or
Gandhi g or whoever inspires you I'm
staying with this old lady she has a
just cute she has a big picture of Obama
on her on her des and she just loves him
you know and she's so she's so inspired
by him so think about someone who
inspires
you think about your teacher think about
how lucky you are to have
one give 7 opinions so
think
about how fortunate you are to be in a
room of people where someone can
seriously say you can sa planets you as
an individual one person in this
room if you follow this course of
instruction
devotedly you you could be someone who
saved not just one world but many worlds
we're talking that kind of staks and
you're in that kind of high stakes thing
you're special
right s uplift your heart uplift your
heart right in the middle of a
meditation in a threee retreat you know
and you've been stuck there for like 6
months and nothing's happening except
the mice got
in uh uplift your heart think out you
know the three of rets you are the you
are one out of it you are one out of 700
million all right you're more special
you're even more special send up up your
[Music]
heart this is a very difficult uh
practice and
um think of something which brings you
life think of something which brings you
life I have a llama who
enjoys wall
Gardens and sunlight and Roses opening
in the sunlight in a world Garden or
French doors with light linen light what
do you call curtain filming curtains and
the light pouring in you see I have a
llama who's turned on by this kind of
thing right so that's the that's the
semma
means try to bring a a similar Vision
into your mind of a sunfill room or of a
sunlight pouring pouring over a garden
sunlight pouring over the roses in a
garden or whatever it turns you on a
neon sign from
McDonald's okay but something bright and
something you
know I don't we don't have a word we
have a word a garden that's filled with
Sunshine lucid's okay light filled
something like that pouring light
pouring radi who said radi yeah that's
good radiant is good some radiant of
just just this is like desperate last
measure right try to think about a light
bulb something
okay this is a beautiful one he says
your mind is a bit down do do the tongue
and tongue
man do the tongue and Tong man what's
that
mean
yeah do a little fantasy where you are
giving people what they want in your
mind it's called th right it's the th
part of
th do a little fantasy where you're
walking around like Santa Claus you know
you have a big bag full of oh what you
want a c line oh here's a c line you
know oh and you do do it as a PR right
you do it on your breath you send the
breath out and you give people things on
your breath which means you have to
brush your teeth and everything
okay if you undertake now I just gave
you a list of antidotes okay that list
should be written down somewhere and you
should memorize it and then when you
have your eyes closed and you're feeling
down which is the most common problem
right then then pull it out your mind
and do one of them probably the only one
you remember is the McDonald's
one then you should go back
to the object which You released
temporarily to go think about the
McDonald's sign all right then go back
to your object you're not allowed to
think about McDonald's sign and then get
up and order some French okay
[Music]
people like you and me he says wrong R
same thing instead a wrong chart people
like you and
me we haven't gotten used to thinking in
the six billion people ter right we
don't think about it very often we're
not used to reflecting in that way that
I am one out of 300 million people who
made it to this room we're not used
to to thinking that way okay it's true
but we're not used to thinking like that
CH on God so in the in the immediate in
the next few days or weeks it's not
going to have a a huge effect on you
right you're you're getting dull in your
meditation you're trying to remember
what did g say to do oh I was supposed
to think that I was one out of 300
million people who had a chance a little
chance
right that's not going to have a boom
boom effect on you right away but keep
trying okay keep keep up that way of
thinking if you get good at thinking
that way or if you get used to thinking
that way uh then just bringing to mind
that will be as if someone had thrown a
bucket of cold water in your face it's
cool right you'll if you get used to
thinking how special you are and it's
not artificial you are special but if
you get used to thinking that then it
will have the effect during your
meditation that a bucket of cold ice
cold water thrown in your face would
have as far as
removing dness subtle dness would that
remove subtle dness let's check okay
Prescott's going to be snowy all right
or it's going to be at least pretty
pretty cold uh so anyone who needs I'll
I'll do the bucket
thing dress warm okay for
that being sick is like really a
disaster for medical especially having a
c because you're coughing and bothering
other people and and you're
slurping so be responsible and and
you'll need to bring lots of warm you
know what do you call
layers okay
if you're really enough you can
say okay good it's a lot like the other
f word okay it means that it's a it's a
sound used in ancient tiet for
like it's just like screaming F you or
something but it's us in rituals
right we say
right so fact
means P me wake
up you
say okay okay no
do pep comes when you uh what you call
don't have an app you know they say can
you give me some French C you know and
excuse me and uh they don't have an F
but in in F and in F they use an F it's
the only two words in their whole
language they
say even they can make
an and then
uh means if you get desperate and you
just can't remove the
dullness picture a sun ripping open your
heart piure son ripping open your heart
like this is getting really bad
like you just can't get your mind up
then picture a sun bursting out of your
heart
like and and then
say out
loud okay see if it helps I say slap
your face at the same time but he didn't
[Music]
say imagine that that is blasting out of
the top of your head and shooting into
the sky like a what do you call those
things they stand from kick and
arrow like
a the ones that come back shuttle okay
like a shuttle launch okay you say pet
and the sun bursts out of your heart and
shoots out of life just shoots out of
the top of your head and disappears into
the at 55,000 ft all
right and then at 55,000 ft it just
melts into the sky and the the whole Sky
becomes Bright Like An atam bomb going
out and then it spreads through the
whole sky this intense light fills the
whole sky around
you do that as many times as you need
okay depending on how bad a day you're
having it maybe up to
100 if you still have a problem it still
doesn't get you out of your dos right
if it still doesn't work and you still
feel
B you can't break out of it
then drop the whole meditation session
drop the session give up the
session go do some physical things that
would help remove the causes of Dum
causes of dness are some kind of
darkness in the mind or you didn't get
enough sleep or your mind is just
overcome with some kind of sadness or
depression in that case you should take
steps to prevent the next meditation
session from being screwed up what are
some drastic measures a three-year
Retreat can take to prevent the
afternoon session from getting screwed
up when they had to break the morning
session because they had this problem
the mind was just too low too down right
he
says go stay somewhere cold good
luck s to go to a high mountain go sit
on a high you have some nice rock
formations in the three Retreat Valley
right up on the ridge go up on the ridge
go climb up the Ridge and sit on the
ridge he says
that go someplace that has expansive and
you have that in you have a the ridge to
to the east right you have that whole
ridge and you have those Cliffs he says
go sit on a cliff or go sit somewhere
expensive P
Chaka uh take walks take long walks
right don't you
don't Splash cold water on your face so
Jing
back into your meditation cabin sit down
and go back into your session go back
into a
session that were those that was an
entire discussion of practical anti
for all right what do you think he's
going on to
next he goes on subtle
Restless go
think he reminds us what subtle
restlessness
is
uh you haven't lost the object but your
mind but your mind is distracted right
we call it water running under ice right
we called it just about to think about
L if you get subtle restlessness the
problem is that youve tightened down
slightly too much you're too tight on
the
say what you
call loosen up a loosen
up but if you loosen up if you try to
loosen up on the object a bit but you
still feel yourself getting
distracted that's sort of a sign that
your restlessness is not as subtle as
you
thought all
right this is a fault of the mind being
a little bit too
happy all right you see he said before
if you felt down you should uplift your
heart or think of things that make you
happy you see I didn't cover that very
much but uh
whatever makes you happy think about
your children or your friends or your
parents or the last award you got or you
know whatever makes you whatever makes
you happy uh bring it to mind but in in
in subtle restlessness
what the mind is too happy the mind is
like I also got ble War you know and uh
okay all right uh
God don't go too far on the happiness
thing God if you get too happy about
some you know thinking about your high
school girlfriend and then it it goes
too far
the
king Buddhist dad right that's the name
of Buddhist
father's father s's father was
named in
tiet G he was about to see emptiness
directly he was on the verge of seeing
emptiness directly and becoming a what's
a
guu stream Mentor he was about to become
a stream Mentor he was on the bridge of
seeing this
directly
M he failed the last minute he failed he
didn't make it why
ran he says don't forget the story of
King sud and then he doesn't tell us the
story this is happening in this text
constantly all the time it's very
frustrating uh so I went and looked it
up due to John br's kindness okay I mean
I have 10 text in here I have a million
pages of text in here so I I can find it
in about 2 minutes in the back of the
car so kindly I have these two people
who drive they drive me around
constantly I work in the back of the car
and find these dumb
spes uh so here you
go Buddha like Lord Jesus right uh in
his time uh he was often not appreciated
I I think there's a story that Jesus
went back to Bethlehem and they tried to
throw him off a clear
he got up in the synagogue and and said
I got it I'm the Son of God and they
took him and tried to throw him off a
cliff right and the same thing happened
with Lord Buddha so you know in the
early years his father was constantly
embarrassed by his son you know he was a
prince he was supposed to be running the
country and he was all sitting under the
trees you know and not washing himself
and just doing nothing
basically uh and it was an embarrassment
for the father later
uh he became famous and people started
to follow him and then he attracted
large groups of Father followers large
groups of followers at which point his
father un what do you call that when you
kicked him out of your
wheel he UND disowned
him yes that's my boy you know
okay okay all right so then came back in
glory probably like Jerusalem they're
throwing the pals on the ground and
everybody's cheering for him you know
and and the dad is like that's my boy I
had the same thing with Mama Christie uh
and her parents that when she spoke
at what was that near near the harbor in
La Catholic
[Music]
universitya yeah her dad's a laola what
do you call it alni alumni alumni and
then uh the night she spoke at Lola to
400 people he was like that's my
daughter you know and you know for 10
years before that it was like I don't
know what the hell she okay same thing
uh so Lord Buddha was like
um he came back in glory he came back
and and all the people of the city are
happy and the father had been studying
and he was on the verge of seeing
emptiness directly but then he got all
he couldn't let go of the thought of how
great his son was and what great jeans
he must
have okay all right he couldn't let it
go he he couldn't stop being proud of
his son in sort of an unhealthy way he
went overboard and then he lost his
medication he was
too too happy got it he was too like
high the mind was too elevated and he he
couldn't focus on this anymore and he
lost it and he didn't become a stream he
lost it very famous unfamous story
okay you won't find it much place I
don't think his father had three
brothers I think and they they did
achieve something but but the father
being the father
failed okay de
me when you get by the way we're just
about we stop what time six I think
we'll take a break in about 5 minutes
all
right
de you don't have to break your
meditation session if you
get if you if you get
subtle distraction all right uh not so
you don't have to break your your
meditation
session who wrote The Heart of the
middle
way that's
entering we
just re okay here now he he has a
suggestion if you
get uh distracted if you get Restless
mind the mind can't stay in the room the
Mind wants to go out and see something
else right that happen then meditate on
what's yeah it means impermanence okay
all things change all things
change every good thing that every
person on this whole earth has ever
gotten they will lose
period okay they're their health their
hair their strength their friends their
family their loved ones their children
their parents their possessions all the
things they work for their whole life
they will
lose if that doesn't bring your mind
down a bit then you have a problem all
right like just reflect a bit on what's
really happening in the world and and
that that's a powerful agent to bring
your mind back if you're like the dad
and you're like oh it's my boy you know
and then you think about the loyal
Auditorium is going to fall down one day
everybody sitting in the auditorium will
be dead they will be skeletons they'll
be eaten by worms in the ground nobody
will remember their name the last photo
of them will be thrown out by some
distant relative who doesn't remember
who that is and that's a story of your
life and that's the story of everybody's
life and that should bring your mind
down a bit that should you not supposed
to get depressed you're just supposed to
bring your mind back in a
bit you can think about the amount of
suffering that you can see in the world
and the amount of suffering that you
cannot see so there are Realms which you
cannot see and there are also suffering
there there is suffering going on in
this world that you can see and there's
a lot of suffering going on that you
cannot see
so bring the Mind down a bit get a
little bit of sadness feel a little bit
what do you call it it's uh what do you
call when you plan
something it's uh it's a sense of
sadness that you
are is a better
word it's
like how do you say consciously but it's
not you are consciously creating some
intent there's a
better yeah deliberate who said that
yeah it's it's a deliberate s and we
never do that right it's a deliberate
sadness can you throw your mind into a
deliberate sadness perp un
purpose why because your mind is to oh I
got this award and and I got this award
and and boy this boy is looking at me
now he's calling me you know and and
then you got to bring your mind down
deliberately with a little bit of
deliberate s right
if you still have the problem if it
doesn't
work you got to
use means drastic measures drastic means
send means like punching somebody you
know send means violently drastic mov
okay uh yeah it's right there s what's
the Sanskrit word for
sent what's the Sanskrit translation for
sent
okay
yoga yoga was once a very drastically
demanding yoga and it was called s it
was called hat because it's so hard the
Tibet translated hat
as thousand years ago hat meant
kickass yoga right here he's saying if
you're still getting uh what do you call
distraction or if you're still Restless
in the mind then sent up use drastic
measures what are
those you say this you get to have
Refreshments here we
go I like it
I really like it I don't know why one
more time one more
time okay that means breath meditation
okay means your breath means breath J J
means going out means going in J it
comes from those of you who care it
comes from
master and it is considered drastic
means
to do
what no for
what yeah to bring the Mind down when
the mind is a little too over the top
right like you just got an award or you
just met a new boyfriend or and you just
can't someone gave you a promotion at
work something good happened to you and
you just can't bring the Mind down okay
unfortunately it doesn't happen that
often right uh but if it happens to
happen then uh then that's the purpose
why you do U and nothing bigger than
that it's a last ditch attempt to bring
the Mind down a little bit and so
somebody got a hold of an Abid Dharma
scripture in Thailand somewhere and they
only had page
63 and it said do breath meditation and
then they've been just doing that uh and
really that was the source of it the
Abid Koshi it came from the Abid D which
reached Thailand and Verma and became
very
and they just got this one little part
of it that was supposed to just be used
when you were too
happy uh and then it just got out of
hand you know it became a whole deal to
to watch your breath all
day uh which doesn't help you that much
okay it's very good for bringing the
Mind back or concentrating the mind or
or as a temporary H as a temporary
drastic means but then you got to go on
to a real meditation object we talked
about that right like like meditate on
some enlightened being or or meditate on
on on emptiness or meditate on universal
Compassion or something
meaningful rather than oxygen coming and
going right that the whole breath
meditation thing there's some kind of I
don't know something happened and it it
blew up it blew got to beig and people
lost the real meditation object it's
only a temporary means to calm the mind
to bring the mind to stability then you
move to a meaningful
object so he starts to
describe
say I just love it I love hear people
say he describes breath meditation he
says the way you do a breath meditation
is
uh when you exhale the breath you think
to yourself oh the breath is leaving my
body
and oh the breath is coming back to my
body oh this is my this is breath number
one and then breath number two and then
breath number three those of you who
know the practice
as a preliminary to meditation in order
to bring your mind down it's traditional
to try to count 10 breaths exhale as the
first half inhale as the SEC second half
try just to count 10 breaths without
thinking about anything else in between
and the the very cruel rule is if you do
think of something else you have to
start over so if you're honest you can't
get past three or four and you could
spend hours like that right in fact it
gets worse as you get tired so um you're
going to uh try to count the breath out
first half in second half count the
bre you won't be able to get to more
than three or four he says okay so the
scripture says it uh
and if you lose it the object at four
you got to start over
again my personal suggestion is you stop
after about 10 minutes okay it's only
going to get worse and you can spend
your whole day like that
okay if you are
able for example to to count to 21
breath purposely okay you will catch
yourself going to 21 by
accident okay that's a it's true it's
funny you say 11 12 and they like oops
you know okay which means you were
thinking about
lunch if you can get to 21 without
thinking of something else which is what
it's a minute minute and a half like
that
okay you have reached the first first
level of
meditation you have reached the first
level of meditation if you can hold the
mind on the breath for 21 breaths
without thinking about something
else I like to be frank I like to make
exceptions for acts of God in in the
insurance business this means things you
can't control if someone slams a door
and your mind goes there and comes right
back I don't start over CU it's not my
fault is it
[Music]
okay there was
a there was a practitioner named a great
practitioner named puno gatso he lived
in ypa ypa is about 10 miles outside of
I almost said Phoenix pla about 10 miles
outside OFA and there are some caves
there and it's famous for meditation
right in anyway this man
from he had a a relative of a brother
who was uh an assistant to Da Sango this
was a very famous Minister prime
minister of toet in the time of the
fifth if you've ever seen those cave
Temple paintings of yoga yoga those were
those were commissioned by s s very very
great minister of Tibet after the G Lama
passed for 5 years he ran Tibet and
didn't tell anybody that the Gama had
passed because he felt that that there
would be a civil war so he had an actor
who would be the Dil Lama and he said he
told everybody they couldn't get close
to him you know sort of a kind of a
rough attendant all right
uh sh they sh
so the Prime Minister and the guy's
relative got some political
trouble and then he was worrying about
his his relative who you know inbet if
you got in trouble you got your eyes GED
out or you got executed or whipped or
you know so he was worried about his uh
relative DNA uh and then uh he started
to do breath meditation and he felt much
better and that's the end of the
story or that he was able what the story
the point of the story is that there
were some very serious personal
lifethreatening things going on in the
family he was distracted and he brought
his mind back by just doing breath
medication he was able to go to stay in
Retreat and keep his mind in Retreat
just by doing this breath meditation so
it does have a good use right
if you try to use this antidote and you
don't succeed then uh for the time being
you can break the
meditation break the
session this is kind of where I'd like
to leave those of you who are going to
be uh away for the week I would kind of
like to leave the the the teaching on
this point all right
he
says before your meditation session
begins make a plan about how many
minutes you plan to meditate for all
right make a plan means make a
[Music]
plan this is really
funny if you make your plan too long if
your plan calls for do you know how many
minutes I was planning to give you this
morning it was 10 I was planning on 10
but at 8 the room felt so so tense that
I had to stop okay so don't go crazy all
right this morning we had to cut from 10
to 8 minutes all right he says un CH if
you go on too
long uh J J later on when you come back
to do your future sessions
something when you see your medit
meditation cushion gupa means you'll
kind of be like e gupa means e and K Jo
means yeah right so you know don't let
your meditation cush become your enemy
you see when you lay eyes on it you feel
tired already or or you walk fed at 8 in
the morning you're like no not today
honey you know I can't do it today you
know don't don't let your meditation
person become someone you don't
like this is a very famous uh T say t t
means a toan saying what do you call it
a cliche
or you call
it yeah
what you say the other one what was the
other one yeah it's like a colloquialism
yeah it's just the same like a they love
pum to they have a saying for everything
okay in fact if you want to learn to
speak toban it's good to memorize that
that's I did that okay
anyway again
again again
it means stop your meditation while
you're having a good
time okay stop stop the meditation while
you're having a good time never stop
meditating on a bad note this also
applies to relationships and it applies
to jobs and it applies to the place
where you live okay if you're having a
problem with your relationship or you're
having a problem with your job or you're
having a problem you don't like the
house you live
stay get over it get happy with the
place and then leave okay fix up the
thing with your
partner okay till it's cheerful and then
leave okay really don't leave things
while they're bad because because you
will take those negative kic seeds to
the next place you go so we solve the
problem with the person and then divorce
them okay all right
resolve problems in your personal life
don't bail out of problems bail out of
successes that's what it sayfe okay and
it applies to meditation also make it
good and then stop don't stop in the
middle of a problem in in life and in
meditation
okay uh stop at the place where you feel
like I could still go for a while okay
this is going great I think I could
squeeze another 10 minutes out of this
stop
there stop there because you'll love
your meditation
question you you'll every time you see
it you'll have you'll part on good terms
right later when you see it you'll feel
happy to do more you know you'll be kind
of like making up excuses to getting a
little more meditation right that's what
you
want not only do you leave it feeling
happy but this is very important in
meditation if you get to be a good
meditator and you're if you stop while
things are going well in the
meditation when you start the next
meditation session it begins to feel
like a continuation of the earlier way
all right that's a nice sign when you
get there when you get to that point you
know your meditation is pretty good you
sit down and it feels like you're just
taking up where you left off right and
that's a you you will get there if you
meditate regularly you will get there
and it just feels like each new
meditation is a continuation of the last
one and then it feels like you're
meditating all the time
if the meditation is not clear and
things aren't going well try to fix it
try to fix it again couple times but if
it doesn't if at that point it's not
going to get
better
say means to uh what you call
it uh 7 comes you and says will you will
you loow me $5 and you say I can't then
they come back to you again and say can
you Lo me $5 say I can't and they keep
coming back means the insisting
continual jackass of insisting all right
means
the if you keep doing this jackass
insistence to fix the meditation when
it's not going it's not going to go uh
you will just get exhausted right
fighting your mind a certain point is
useless you will just get
exhausted and later on uh when you sit
down to meditate you'll take off from
where you were which is tired
right he gives an example of a llama who
had the same sort of thing happen he
left something at a point that was a
little bit sad and then he had trouble
bringing coming back to it here's the
example the Lama's name
[Music]
was and he was teaching a very famous
book by the
early the first Buddhist ofet
called These are the miscellaneous
sayings of theas the first G of okay
he was giving a j j means uh it's a
teaching where you just go and read the
book out loud and the blessing of the
words entered the mind of the audience
okay he was giving a ja a ja is H for
Jack means your holy
tongue you don't call
it in to Lama you say your job your
honorable
job uh
[Music]
to a line which
said these are the times in the world
when people should try to concentrate on
improving their own
heart and not worry so much about
improving others Hearts he got to this
line
okay sansu sh and he started to
weep couldn't stop crying just started
crying and he couldn't continue with the
with the moon with the oral
transmission so they had to quit for the
day right Chan he came back the next day
and he got up on the throne and he
thought about where he was the day
before he started crying again and he
couldn't go he couldn't continue Okay so
it's an example for your meditation
session is low or depressed and then if
you if you leave it there and you start
again the next day like that it's almost
like the nature of things that you will
start with a depress state of mind so
don't leave it while it's low
okay don't don't leave it while you're
crying you see cuz you'll pick it up
crying the next day
okay means same thing happen the day
after
so that's a story
that so I'm going to leave it there okay
cuz before you get tired of me uh cuz
then you'll be tired of me when we start
again
uh look at the poster study the poster
okay uh get used to the poster and put
it up in your room somewhere all right m
and and and review your notes and and
think about this class don't just there
there's a joke in bed they say don't
leave the class at the door don't leave
the class at the threshold of the door
okay uh keep it with you especially go
over which
problem which of the
five which of the five would I most like
you to work with number three right so
subtle dullness and subtle uh
restlessness okay I want you to study
those antidotes and think about those an
okay and do some
meditation and and watch your own mind
for sub th see if you can catch your own
mind doing subtle dness that's your
practical homework for the week okay
those of you who are flying
away and I'm personally I I feel really
really happy about this class
and I feel really happy about the future
prospects of this class you know I I
feel like it's a really good way to
spend the next 10 years of our Liv you
know to be doing this every once in a
while together and uh so thank you for
coming